Mary Webb Papers, 1898-1926
Mortimer Rare Book Room, William Allan Neilson Library, Smith College
Mary Webb Papers
1898-1926
Webb, Mary Gladys Meredith, 1881-1927
8
1 box (0.5 linear ft.)
Mortimer Rare Book Room Smith College Northampton, MA
English poet and novelist acknowledged by the Institut Français in 1926 for "the best imaginative work in prose or verse descriptive of English life by an author who has not gained sufficient recognition." Includes 30 holographs and 58 typescript drafts of 80 poems as well as a holograph draft of a book review.
Mary Webb was born in Leighton-under-the-Wrekin, Shropshire, England, on March 25, 1881 to George Edward and Sarah Alice Meredith. She was educated at home by her schoolmaster father, but spent two years in Southport attending a private school. Webb suffered from Graves's disease throughout her adult life, her most serious attack keeping her bedridden for several years at the age of twenty. She married Henry Webb in June 1912, and lived in Shropshire until 1921 when the couple moved to London. The Institut Français presented her with the Femina/Vie Heureuse prize for Precious Bane in 1926, acknowledging "the best imaginative work in prose or verse descriptive of English life by an author who has not gained sufficient recognition."
Her writings include the novels The Golden Arrow (London: Constable, 1916; New York: Dutton, 1935), Gone to Earth (London: Constable, 1917; New York: Dutton, 1917), The House in Dormer Forest (London: Hutchinson, 1920; New York: Doran, 1921), Seven for a Secret, A Love Story (London: Hutchinson, 1922; New York: Doran, 1923), Precious Bane (London: Cape, 1924; New York: Dutton, 1926), Armour Wherein He Trusted (London: Cape, 1929; New York: Dutton, 1929), a collection of essays entitled The Spring of Joy (London and Toronto: Dent/New York: Dutton, 1917; New York: Dutton, 1937), a poetry collection Fifty-one Poems Hitherto Unpublished in Book Form (London: Cape, 1946; New York: Dutton, 1947) and two anthologies Poems and the Spring of Joy (London: Cape, 1928; New York: Dutton, 1929) and Mary Webb: Collected Prose and Poems, edited by Gladys Mary Coles (Shropshire: Wildings, 1977).
The Mary Webb Papers contain 30 holographs and 58 typescript drafts of 80 poems as well as a holograph draft of a book review. The majority of these poems were published in 51 Poems (London: Cape, 1946; New York: Dutton, 1947), a posthumously published collection. The bulk of the material is undated; those works which are dated span the years 1898-1926. Twelve manuscripts were presented to Smith College by David J. and Barbara Holmes on March 29, 1994 in memory of Ruth Mortimer, Class of 1953. The book review was purchased from the Book Press on July 18, 1990, in a red cloth folder with the bookplate of H. Bradley Martin. The remaining 77 manuscripts were purchased in May 1994 from David J. Holmes on the Fund established by Hillier Krieghbaum, in memory of his wife Katherine Lancaster Krieghbaum, Class of 1938. The 77 manuscripts were housed in a blue full leather clamshell box and in a green cloth slipcase with the bookplates of H. Bradley Martin.
This collection is organized into two series:
I. Review by Mary Webb
II. Poems by Mary Webb, 1898-1926
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The Mary Webb Papers are the physical property of the Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College. Literary rights, including copyright, belong to the authors of works or their legal representatives.
History of the Collection
Twelve manuscripts were presented to Smith College by David J. and Barbara Holmes on March 29, 1994 in memory of Ruth Mortimer, Class of 1953. The book review was purchased from the Book Press on July 18, 1990, in a red cloth folder with the bookplate of H. Bradley Martin. The remaining 77 manuscripts were purchased in May 1994 from David J. Holmes on the Fund established by Hillier Krieghbaum, in memory of his wife Katherine Lancaster Krieghbaum, Class of 1938. The 77 manuscripts were housed in a blue full leather clamshell box and in a green cloth slipcase with the bookplates of H. Bradley Martin.
Search Terms
Webb, Mary Gladys Meredith, 1881-1927.; Women novelists, English--20th century.; Women poets, English--20th century.
- Series I. Review by Mary Webb, undated, (1 item)
  Series I. consists of one holograph entitled "Plus que de l'esprit" which is a review of Ariel (1924) and Mape (1926) by Andre Maurois (Folder 1).
- Series II. Poems of Mary Webb, 1898-1926, undated, (88 items)
  Series II. consists of 88 holograph and typescript drafts of 80 poems. Two drafts exist for the following titles: "Buds," "The Dance," "The Footpath," "Hazel Buds," "Praise," "The Thought," and "The White Moth". Forty-five of these poems are published in Fifty-one Poems (London: Cape, 1946; New York: Dutton, 1947), six are published in Poems and the Spring of Joy (London: Cape, 1928; New York: Dutton, 1929) and twenty-nine are unpublished.
- Series I. Review by Mary Webb, undated, (1 item)
  - "Plus que de l'esprit": holograph, signed, undated, 6 leaves (6 pages); 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Address: Spring Cottage, Lythe Hill, Shrewsbury.
    Book Press
- Series II. Poems of Mary Webb, 1898-1926, undated, (88 items)
  - "Absence": typescript, 1921 Jun, 2 leaves (2 pages); 26 cm or smaller. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 42-3.
    Krieghbaum, Blue case
  - "Adam": typescript, signed, 1919, 6 leaves (6 pages); 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Unpublished.
  - "Alder Buds": holograph, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 10 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 22
  - "Among the hills": holograph, signed, undated, 1 leaf (2 pages); 14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Unpublished. Address: Penrose, Landemann Circus, Weston-super-mare.
  - "Apple-blow": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Published in 51 Poems, pg. 41.
  - [Autumn, 1914]: typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 19 cm. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 45.
  - [The Beacon]: typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 10 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 39.
  - "The Beautiful House": holograph, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 12 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 11.
  - [Beauty and Terror]: typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 fragment); 12 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 20.
  - "Beloved! Beloved! I hear in the darkness...": holograph, signed, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - [Bounty]: typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 12 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 14.
  - [Buds]: holograph, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 8 cm. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 32. Variant title: "Earth's Trainband".
  - "Buds": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Caterina to Camoens": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 11 cm. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "A Conqueror": typescript, signed, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 27 cm. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - [The Dance]: typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 23 cm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 15.
  - "The Dance": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Dawn": holograph, 1902 Jun, 1 leaf (2 pages); 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Desolation": typescript, corrected, 1909 Jan, 1 leaf (1 page); 13 cm. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Published in 51 Poems, pg. 24. Address: Maesbrook.
  - "An Estray": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 23 cm. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 59. Additional stanza and manuscript note.
    Holmes
  - [The Fawn]: holograph, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 11 cm. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Unpublished. Manuscript title: "Pastel".
  - "The Fawn": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 12 cm. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "The Flockmaster": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 20 cm. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 61.
  - "The Footpath (I)": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "The Footpath (II)": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Foreboding": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 48.
  - "The Gates of Green and Gold": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - [The Goblet]: holograph, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (2 pages); 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 60.
  - "The Grape-Blue Hills": typescript, undated, 1 leaf ( 1 page); 12 cm. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 57.
  - [The Great Wind]: typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 13 cm. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 16.
  - "Harps in Heaven": typescript, signed, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Harvest Song": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 20 cm. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 31. Address: [Penrose, Landemann] Circus, [Weston-super-]mare.
  - "Hazel Buds": holograph, uncorrected, undated, 1 leaf (1page); 9 cm. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 29.
  - "Hazel Buds": typescript, uncorrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Heavy Silence": holograph, uncorrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 7 cm. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 23.
  - "The Heritage": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 11 cm. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - "Hill Pastures": holograph, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 27 cm. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 54.
  - "In April": typescript, signed, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Published in Poems and The Spring of Joy, p. 30-31.
  - "Into a broken heart...": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 16 cm. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - "Isolde": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 40.
  - "I watched him in the loud and shadowy lane...": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 9 cm. (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - "I worship the earth and the airs that blow...": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - [Lilies in the Valleys]: holograph, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 20 cm. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 34.
  - "The Lost Orchard": typescript, corrected undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 20 cm. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 56. Manuscript note: Sunday Pictorial, 1920.
  - "A Lover of Roses": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 13 cm. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Published in 51 Poems, p.46.
  - "Magic": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 50.
  - "Master of the Coppice": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 15 cm. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 9.
  - [The Mountain Tree]: typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 8 cm. (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 12.
  - "My Love is in the Mountains": typescript, signed, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 18 cm. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 53.
  - "Nature's Dogmatists": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 17 cm. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 17.
  - "New Year's Day": holograph, corrected, signed, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 44.
  - "Night in the Open Air": holograph, 1911 May, 1 leaf (1 page); 23 cm. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 21. Address: Radbrook.
  - "On the Hills": holograph, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); p. 13 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 30.
  - [On the Wild Hill]: holograph, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (2 pages); 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 55.
  - "The plovers are shrill tonight...": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 7 cm. (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - "The Poplar Tree": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 18 cm. (Box 1, Folder 57)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 62.
  - "Praise": holograph, signed, 1920, 1 leaf (1 page); 23 cm. (Box 1, Folder 58)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 63.
  - "Praise": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - "Quick Swallows, cosmopolitans of the air...": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - [Reflections]: holograph, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 9 cm. (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - "The rivers ran from rock to rock...": typescript, corrected, signed, 1921, 1 leaf (1 page); 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 62)
    Unpublished. Address: Leinster Square.
  - "Rondeau Redouble": holograph, 1909, 1 leaf (2 pages); 23 cm. (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - [Rose-Berries]: typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 64)
    Published in Poems and The Spring of Joy, p. 36. Manuscript title: "The Rose-Berry"
    Krieghbaum, Green case
  - [Sallow-Catkins]: typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 24 cm. (Box 1, Folder 65)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 28.
  - [The Secret Joy]: holograph, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 15 cm. (Box 1, Folder 66)
    Published in Poems and The Spring of Joy, p. 29. Manuscript title: "Freemasonry".
  - "The Sedge-warbler": holograph, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 20 cm. (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - "Shepherd's Song": holograph, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 16 cm. (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - "Snowdrop Time": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page; 7 cm. (Box 1, Folder 69)
    Published in Poems and The Spring of Joy, p. 39.
  - "Spring": holograph, 1898, 1 leaf (2 pages); 11 cm or less (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - "Summer Remembered": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 71)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 36-7.
  - "Sunset": holograph, uncorrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 72)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 49
  - "Thanksgiving": holograph, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 30 cm. (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - "There are the pastures of sleep...": typescript, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 12 cm. (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - [The Thought]: holograph, uncorrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 15 cm. (Box 1, Folder 75)
    Published in Poems and The Secret of Joy, p. 103. Manuscript title: "The Messenger"
  - "The Thought": typescript, signed, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 23 cm. (Box 1, Folder 76)
    Published in Poems and The Spring of Joy, p. 103.
  - "Thunderbolts": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 20 cm. (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - "To G.D.M.": holograph, corrected, 1919 Sep 15, 1 leaf (1 page); 20 cm. (Box 1, Folder 78)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 51.
  - "To Life": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - "To my Dear": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 80)
    See: "Sunset"
  - "Two Faiths": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page), 19 cm. (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - "Unfinished Embroidery": holograph, corrected, n.y. Jan 5, 1 leaf (1 page); 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - "Very Early": typescript, corrected, signed, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 83)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 58.
  - [The White Moth]: holograph, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - "The White Moth": typescript, undated, 2 leaves (2 pages); 25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - "The Wild Rose": typescript, corrected, signed, ca. 1912, 1 leaf (1 page); 14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 86)
    Published in Poems and The Spring of Joy, p. 111.
  - "The Wondrous Voice:" holograph, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page) 2 pages; 20 cm. (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - "The Wood-Witch": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 88)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 33.
  - "The Yellow-Hammer": typescript, corrected, undated, 1 leaf (1 page); 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 89)
    Published in 51 Poems, p. 10.